um but the date doesn't really matter
because the information is general and
applies in 1750 and in 2050
so don't worry about the data if you're
listening to this Mastermind later
um
we can certainly
see if we can provide a replay
um and I might offer it at a later time
so today's Mastermind and a couple of
words to who I am I'm Professor Johanna
Sophia actually professor of film and
um educator professor of Education
Waldorf in particular so a dual thing
there nothing to do with nourishment
except that
my
purpose has always been to move toward a
healthier happier more collaborative
world and today we're just talking about
collaborating with our own body and with
our own biology and therefore this
Mastermind is titled
self-heal for cheap
because healing our biology is not
necessarily expensive people do all
sorts of really expensive stuff out
there but I'm not that person
so
I'm the person who
finds ways that are close to Nature and
close to
simple but yet sophisticated enough that
they're delicious so I'm very much into
culture and creating delicious things
even for cheap
so we don't want to be boring or just
live on
rice and beans or
um
yeah that's why we're humans we have
creativity and we make things beautiful
and we make things delicious and we make
things smelling good and
and feeling good and looking good all of
the above
should also be applied to food
production and self-healing but
self-healing is not only food so
we'll also in today's Mastermind talk
about the five modalities that we need
to self-heal and nourishment is only one
of them
so we'll get to that in a little bit let
me first talk a little bit about life on
planet Earth what do you need to talk
about life on planet Earth hello we all
live on planet Earth with trees and
animals and plants and everything
because
I need to talk about how it actually
works
and while we're all looking at it like
I'm looking out of my window I see grass
and trees and I need another sea another
building a little bit further down and
I see biology out there even in my house
I'm looking at an orchid plant I'm
looking at something that I'm showing
you later that's sprouting you on my
table
I'm looking at plants
I'm looking at my hands all of it is of
course biology
and all of it is of course alive because
we haven't killed it yet
actually the irony of today's talk is
that
even
in death there is of course new lives
there are the decomposers Etc so let me
start with
everything on planet Earth
is
alive in a way it reproduces itself even
stones and dirt and sand
are somewhat alive because they're still
Modified by what by wind and water and
chemicals in the air and of course by
human hands
so
but how does biology work
biology
works because it constantly reproduces
itself
all the time it constantly reproduces
itself when it stops reproducing itself
it begins to die off
in fact when All Elements of Life in our
human body oh here's my cat my son's cat
actually that wants to participate
in The Mastermind so you will hear her
talk a little bit and I won't
um react to it necessarily
so all of course she's alive too and
she's reproducing herself all the time
too
why am I saying where life reproduces
itself all the time what does life
consist of yes darling you can't
you can't make a noise here and distract
everybody
um
because
what is life made of it is made out of
tiny little entities we call cells
what do these cells do
they constantly reproduce if they're
healthy cells and the old ones and they
also throw out the old ones or decompose
the old ones in what we call excrement
or urine
or exhale
which is another thing that gets me of
course to something that we recently
should have
understood but did not for the most part
all our reproduced cell tissue
also
has a life cycle and that's another
thing what is life life is always in
Cycles always in Cycles it germinates
there are germs
it grows
and it's
dies
and that's part and then it provides
fertilizer for the next growth and it
can be a different type of life right or
excrement typically does not lead to new
growth of humans but it's great it
creates life of plants and good soil Etc
if we were in a natural cycle which we I
think we're going to understand soon and
get back to not back to get forward to
because we didn't really understand it
at least not in the western culture
um for hundreds of years
thousands probably
um
so life is constant reproduction now who
is reproducing life all the time
and here we get two
tiny little entities also called germs
isn't that ironic
what are these kind of germs
they are
fungi and bacteria
and
what we call viruses which is debatable
and which a tiny little and that help
clean out the body
and
they are also
um
what's the last group it's a whole group
of tiny little worms and critters with
some of which we call parasites but
they're actually part of that which I
called in this morning's email that I
sent out the Symphony of life
or the Symphony of biology so when all
these little entities work together then
we get life and when they're in tune
imagine a big Symphony right when all
the instruments are off
key
we call that cacophony noise it hurts
our ears we go like ah
and when they're in Harmony when they're
in tune and this one provides this sound
and that one provides that sound and
that one provides that sound then we get
a beautiful Symphony Of Life
and that Symphony of life is a question
of balance
things all these little critters and
elements have to be in good balance have
to be collaborating now if we throw in
killers that kill off one part of these
or majority of these little entities we
call germs or bacteria and
and fungi and viruses and parasites
little worms and all those kind of
Little Critters that actually your very
body is made of to the majority of cells
only some of those cells 30 to 40
percent there's there's debate you know
some people say only 10 to 15 percent
are actually human cells particular to
the human genetic makeup
so
we have this we are this or our body is
this entity of lots of little entities
that
collaborate and when they're in Symphony
and making harmonic beautiful sounds
then we have what we call health or
Wellness right when they are out of tune
or one is dominating and
killing the others and inflammation
arises to try and bring balance back
heat arises fever we call that fever to
try and put things Back in Balance then
we call that state of being sick or
illness
and we have thousands of definitions for
this illness
and people always say well does your
scenario does your approach work for
arthritis well what about migraine well
what about
um diabetes well what about cancer well
what about you what about you
thousands of diagnoses
and yet
the definition that
the Symphony of life in our body is off
kilter
explains all of it
of course when we have an accident and
we have a an arm cut off and we need to
put that back together and it will grow
back together because we have
sophisticated
um
surgery
that enable us that we need that
sophisticated surgery to
get that arm back I actually had a
neighbor at one of when I lived in the
Catskills who had been
shot in the arm you know hunting you
know as they do up in the mountains and
his arm was literally severed and they
sewed it back on so it was shorter but
it was somewhat functioning again and of
course that's miraculous now was it
necessary to shoot around and shoot that
poor Ben's arm off
that's questionable
so in any case
our body
can manage even that it grows back
together it finds a way to rebalance
even that amputated arm
that can be
surgically put back on
so
our body is a self-healing instrument
I'm sure you've heard that before it
heals itself it's whole operation is
it's as if the instruments constantly
tune themselves
isn't that a beautiful example you don't
have to go with me or and tune your
strings and your various instruments but
you can leave that to your body
if
and now we're getting to the five things
that I announced we we're going to talk
about
if those five things are available to
the body to rebalance all the way
to tune its instruments all the way
to get back into a healthy reproduction
of new cell tissue so that we can be
in our
excuse me 50 60s 70s 80s 90s and we have
people in here from who is the youngest
Who is younger than 40 in here give me a
text
and who's older than 70 in here I
already know
Shirley is Nancy is yeah and she just
went running so keeping this body
in regenerative
reproductive mode all the time okay we
women can't have babies anymore after
that era ends but we have to and can
reproduce the new cell tissue all the
time so that we can stay in a healthy
mode
so and of course all of that we learn in
my super happy body course that is a 12
month course and we go and walk
everybody through to their new Mission
and we have one person in here who just
is about to finish and do her thesis her
final paper that's Linda Roser
and she has to deliver her 20-page paper
and presentation of her new business
being a health coach
um
so that's what we do in that class but
let's get to
the five elements that are necessary for
a healthy
regenerative body
so we we started out with what is life
what creates life we can also say what
creates life on planet Earth you know
people always say oh it's because there
is water oh it's because there is
sunshine oh it's because there is air oh
it's because there is
soil and life in the soil
now I happen to think neither the
religious story nor the darwinistic
story I happen to think that
if you will we chose this planet
to Incarnate on to have this experience
on planet Earth which is
just phenomenal because we have senses
that are
nowhere else to be had right other than
in this body we can see we can hear we
can taste we can smell we can think we
can we can feel texture we can project
we can love we can I mean that's really
the biggest thing right we can love we
can connect we can and What Makes Us
humans in my view is we can create
and then people say well animals are
also creative look at the beaver Etc
mind you I love all animals and I don't
eat them
um but
the beaver cannot decide to next year
build the Beaver House on a tree
we can
now we do a lot of nonsense with our
creative abilities
as I've said often
we do a lot of
destructive Creations because
we got into an era of dominance and of
hierarchies and of Empires and of
defining ourselves by what we own
instead of by Who We Are
I think we're evolving to that new
definition of who we are but back to
what are the five modalities we need to
be
regenerating ourselves in a healthy
manner
sweetheart she wants to go out and I
know she knows that I'm
typically running to open the door for
her but not right now
so
um
those five things are
the elements
fresh air sunshine
good
electromagnetic fields from the soil
because that's something that's kind of
the next level of understanding of what
biology is
but I can't go too much into it today
so Sunshine air soil and of course water
now all of those things well sunshine
you could argue is not necessarily alive
but it allows everything on planet Earth
to come alive
um
how do we do that so modality number one
is exposing ourselves to Nature and to
me that all comes together in breathing
yes baby
what am I supposed to do Linda are you
going to take over me so I can let her
out
Windows too shy
um
so
there's water and there's air and yes we
need water to be alive but we can
self-heal with exposing ourselves to all
those elements and breathing is
something that we forget
because we have to do it all the time
right if we thought too much about it we
would probably
be too self-conscious
we have to do it all the time to stay
alive
and to put the oxygen deeply into your
lungs without inhibition without having
things in front of our faces or having
closed windows that are so tight that
the indoor air is toxic
and I don't get how people don't
understand that everything you do to
inhibit your oxygen uptake
um is destructive to your Healthy cell
reproduction your entire body requires
oxygen all the time and of course what
is in the air
is the air dead
is the air
not alive what's in there
trillions and trillions of again
bacteria and Little Critter viruses and
tiny little entities that are alive
if you sanitize the air and kill off
everything in it if you have
um a space for example for some computer
work you know that is required take out
the oxygen
and the aliveness in the air you cannot
live
you have to
then
yeah get an oxygen tank or in order to
keep you alive you can of course live on
an oxygen tank for a limited amount of
time
underwater for example right so here we
go
there she is
all right baby I I'm not dealing with
you on my desk right now
so
there's another live being that wants to
be
taken care of
um
so when we kill off the air it also
becomes
un alive and non
supportive of our
of our regeneration so healthy air is
absolutely important when we walk under
trees of course we don't just get the
fresh exhaled so to speak of the tree
but we also get the electromagnetic
fields of trees and plants and soil
around us so number one of the five
things is breathing and of course I
teach the um Wim Hof method
even though I'm not certified so I
shouldn't say that but I love him and I
know that he would approve what I do
um
so deep breathing
sunshine
good good water I get my water I
actually drive to get my water from a
spring it comes directly out of the Rock
and is highly mineralized because it
comes directly out of the Rock and
tastes fantastic
um
so
and along with the breathing actually
goes something else
um a new colleague of mine with whom I'm
collaborating just asked me this morning
why why why cold shower every morning
why not fresh hot and then cold and I
said well you know we live in so much
heat we have heated Apartments we have
heated cars in the northern hemisphere
right now and so we don't need to
go into heat first we can just jump into
the cold water but of course our body
also produces heat all the time and cold
water
enhances that
again that reproducts that cell
reproduction it rushes our blood to
throughout the body
um
as does running outside like Nancy I
just did before
The Mastermind
okay number one Sunshine breathing Water
and Air number two is nourishment mind
you these are not
um in hierarchical order they're all
equally important nourishment
is vitamins minerals proteins
phytonutrients and nourishment is also
of course air
and water so I made this little drawing
you know and then I thought oh it's five
parts it's like the little
human you know head arms legs and
they're these five elements that are
necessary to heal ourselves
so
very briefly what makes the best
nourishment when is food best nourishing
our human body
and I always used to say well ask
anybody on the street what do you think
is the healthiest for humans to eat
and they'll say fruits and vegetables
and they'll think
of
fresh fruits probably but dead
vegetables why am I saying dead
vegetables
because they think of cooked spinach and
steamed broccoli or baked potatoes Etc
because our culture
has of course developed all these
wonderful Cuisines of cooked Foods
now
when you Analyze This scientifically
then of course you realize that
all life on planet Earth feeds on other
live elements
the tree inhales and brings up living
water from the soil with minerals and
nutrients gets Living Air
all animals eat
um my dear friend Dr Clement always says
Brian Clement always says you know there
are 11 million species on the planet
only one of them eats dead stuff
who's that
Mal she she does because when we feed
her that prepared stuff then you know of
course
um that's not what she would eat in
nature in nature she would eat fresh
live other creatures and
some people will say well what about the
hyena
it's
corpses carcasses but by the time the
hyena eats them
there's watch in the carcasses for the
most part
little decomposers and worms and so none
of that is sanitized and dead like it is
sanitized when we pasteurize something
so just
very quickly
the healthiest food
we can possibly consume
that helps our cell tissue to regenerate
quickly is raw fresh definitely must be
organic because we don't want to put
poisons back into the body that we're
trying to clear out
um
fruits vegetables seeds and
um grains and legumes I mean they make
all these differences between the
different food groups but it's basically
plants why am I not including meat
should we eat raw fish raw meat
and then I always say yeah of course if
you want to go run out and catch a
rabbit cut it with your teeth suck out
the blood chew on those sinews and non
those bones
and especially the intestines you have
to eat the intestines first with all the
poop in it because that's the healthy
part for the for the predator
no not appealing
oh how come
I don't understand I thought you think
you need to eat animals
that's strange you don't like that
we have evolved to make animals taste
like plants oh okay because we can't
really digest them
with all that poop
and all that
tough stuff
and of course there are lots of reasons
why you know when you again look at the
biology of this human body it has the
biology of what we call an herbivore it
has a long intestine it doesn't have an
esophagus that opens up to let large
lumps of Flesh go through which is what
carnivores have from the big birds to
the bear you know they're very much
omnivores but you know they have an
esophagus that means a throat that opens
up to swallow whole lumps of Flesh and
sinews and parts of Bones and
cartilage and all of that right and
what's in the stomach to digest all of
that
hydrochloric acid
so that breaks everything down okay
um
next so let's just go move on with where
basically herbivores and yes can you
survive meat of course you can but it
will shorten your life and it will
shorten your
um
it will shorten your health or impede
your health right so Nancy and I know
all about that Linda too and I'm sure a
lot of you in here do as well but
check it out yes darling I need to read
my paper she sits of course on where I'm
busy doing something
all right so we need breathing we need
nourishment we need movement why
movement because all of life is movement
and if we don't allow our body to
challenge the muscle tissue
we degenerate
in the muscle tissue and the heart is a
is a muscle and
if you take my case I have a little hole
in my heart and so I've always had
issues that I'm not as strong as I'm
supposed to be not as good in sports Etc
so I had to make an extra effort to go
running to work out Etc to get that
heart muscle to function properly and we
can do that
um so movement also cheap if you do it
by yourself or you sign up for
um somebody who does it online on
YouTube or anywhere else so that you can
follow a program or you create your own
um or you follow my programs I have lots
of Fitness over 50 programs and other
such things where and my um my twitch
Channel
has workouts so that you can just follow
another workout and or go running go on
long walks Etc so movement is number
three number four is rest rest is
absolutely crucial as we all know
because that's when a lot of the pushing
out of the old stuff happens
the Regeneration in my understanding
works all the time but pushing out the
dead Parts happens at night or whenever
we sleep
and of course rest is not just sleeping
it's also meditation or meditative work
deep relaxation I do a whole workout on
deep relaxation
and
the allowing the biology to do its own
thing and allowing the emotions to slow
down and the mind to slow down so that
everything can
awaken the beauty in this
self-regenerating biology
so and the last number five in my list
is Joy
and ecstasy
and happiness
and gratitude and love love is of course
in all of that
if we don't have that before other
elements all may not do anything may
just not work
so
when you don't have a way to be
joyfully
living getting up in the morning and
looking forward to the day
of course you know going out into nature
creating things with other human beings
getting together that's when
all the other elements
decrease in efficacy
in terms of helping you rejuvenate
so
all of these are really cheap modalities
right so I said self heal for cheap
except we have this idea that food is
expensive when it's healthy
and I wanted to give you a few ideas as
to how food can be inexpensive
and that is
when we
she's on my pad and on my book
all right darling you can stay yes you
can stay I've worked around you
um
what are some of the foods that we can
make for ourselves and share with others
that are both super delicious and very
inexpensive
so Modell I mean food number one
where are my sprouts
so I'm going to I'm going to share my
screen hopefully that works
um
share
why am I not seeing this thing that big
I want to see this big
huh
can you see the jar with the sprouted
lentils and the mango
I can't
yes
beautiful all right
um I have two screens here so I'm
getting confused what you can actually
see thereof so do you see these
beautiful lentil Sprouts here how they
are totally green and sticking out the
top of the jar
this hole
jar it's it's a it's a gallon jar so
it's big is actually
created by putting
I think three tablespoons of lentils in
there
that's all it takes to create a whole
gallon Jar full of living plants
and they taste
very much like peas I find also I just
made mung bean sprouts and they're also
very much like they taste like peas but
I also use them to mix them of course
mix them into your salad chop them up
when they're this big lentil Sprouts
start to get tough so you might want to
chop them up so that they're not too
chewy
but there are lots of other seeds that
we can Sprout and create beautiful
trash plant life even in an apartment
even Etc even
um
in the Deep the depth of winter right
and we will have fresh plants that are
inexpensive they go into lots of
different dishes too for example my beet
burgers are now also made with sprouted
lentils or sprouted mung beans
um and these burgers are dehydrated and
dehydrated so
sprouting and I put this mango here
because
um I cut off the top and saw that it
wasn't ripe enough
and I put it back on
and
lo and behold it literally grew back
together
so that again verifies and validifies my
story of the separate arm that grows
back together right nature does that
everywhere
so this
piece that you see here
cut off literally grew back onto the
mango even though it was lying around in
my house
but it's an organic mango and that is
very important because its entire life
force has not been
nuked or chemically altered or
waxed right so
um that's why that works
so the the mango is still alive even
though it has
lived through being picked somewhere in
Florida and or even or Mexico or
wherever it's coming from has traveled
and is now
in a store and then in my car and then
in my living room or kitchen and lying
there growing back together it's
miraculous it's beautiful and again
that's why it's so important to have
um living foods and I teach that in my
upcoming course
um
the learn to be more self-sustaining I
teach sprouting and fermenting and
foraging and dehydrating and preparing
things for freezing and preparing
dehydrated Goods
um so that you can always have stacks of
food
and be more self-sustaining
all right so I also wanted to show you
um
foraging of course here's fresh
dandelions from outside these are real
wild dandelions not from the store
but
foraging allows you to and I mean people
even forage in Central Park right Nancy
yeah
um
and hopefully the city doesn't spray
there
but um of course in most nature parks uh
you're pretty safe to go and pick
because things are not spread actually I
see here on the side there's also a
this is probably a um
garlic mustard leaf
um so yeah there's lots of foraging that
goes on our our learn to be self
sustaining course starts on again I have
to dig it out from under my darling here
starts on
February 1st so that's in a few days and
um
the cost of that is only
497 dollars for a two-month course with
all of these different elements that
we're learning
um
and I'll I'll send you all the links so
you can decide what to participate in if
you want to
then there is
yeah then there is dehydrating and
do we have no that social that's a
smoothie
one is a Savory smoothie I call it
gazpacho smoothie again we can make this
with
foraged greens and then add cucumber
zucchini
um and things from the store that you
might like or a little avocado
Etc and we get a beautiful gazpacho
Savory a salty
um garlicky if you want if you like that
smoothie and a sweet smoothie so when we
do our smoothie cleanses the next one I
think is coming up on February 16th
and for seven to seven day smoothie
cleanse
um we will start out making two
smoothies and these are both gallon
containers so you have not quite I think
they're more like three-quarter
gallons
um you will have a sweet smoothie and a
Savory smoothie and the sweet one is all
um purple because there are blueberries
in there obviously blueberries come in
in fresh and in
Frozen and organic frozen blueberries
are actually quite good in
in content and sometimes we can find
them really inexpensively talking about
cheap again I get my frozen blueberries
from Aldi's which has good organic stuff
believe it and the price is right so you
can afford to have your blueberries
and they're just not all pretty perfect
but who needs pretty perfect the
nutrients are there
all right
um
then yeah
and then we have
yeah these are the more luxurious Foods
this is this is a
um this is on my website you can go and
find
um the freeze it's still free
um book
um raw some chocolates
and they're 21 recipes I think
of
um
desserts and actually also a couple of
savory things that include raw cacao so
they're they're chocolate goodies this
is an orange chocolate cake and
um this is my Oreo
moose and
um Ginger brownies are an old
product of mine so good
we have talked about the five elements
and we have talked about the biology of
life and regeneration
let me stop the sharing oh this is oh I
need to mention this quickly
um the big life-changing program that's
the 12 month program and today only or
as you watch this Mastermind
today only you can get into that program
for only two hundred dollars per month
um I still have it here for three three
thousand or
297 a month
yeah it's always cheaper if you can
afford to pay
up front
um
but um yeah today is 200 only all right
I want to go to
do you have any questions and I'm going
to stop sharing and putting us back on
here
all right
um
are there any questions
um some people I don't know TJ and Ultra
um
would you like to
ask
any questions
regarding what we were talking about
so
yeah because I can I can talk forever if
you don't have any questions
I was wondering like if you
[Music]
um
I I actually thought this might be more
about
um like Homeopathy do you you know think
about those kinds of alternative
naturopathy Homeopathy herbs
um
for me it's
like I don't really see doctors at all I
don't really have a need and also I know
they only take four hours of nutrition
class yeah and I've studied this for 50
years so I think I know a little bit
more than they might yeah
um but for me it's um Let me let me
answer that question for me
um I grew up with Homeopathy because I
grew up in a waldorf household in an as
a pacifist household
um where Homeopathy was the only thing
we used I've never been vaccinated I've
never had allopathic medicines really
until of course I went through my
growing years as a young woman and had
to try out some stuff but um
but the the
um my answer to Homeopathy when people
who are on poor diets ask me well what
about Homeopathy I always say no
herb no
drop no and Homeopathy of course is not
really the Herbal Essence it's the
energetic Essence in
in the
the respective plant life that it's
derived from but none of that can
override a burger or a steak when it's
made out of meat none of it can override
or fix something that you have created
or or a donut for that matter from from
Dunkin Donuts
I'm not picking on anybody in particular
here but you know none of
medicines that are herbal and natural I
think they can enhance when we are
already on a healthy diet and a healthy
lifestyle but the healthy lifestyle is
what the biology needs first in order to
then also be further enhanced and pushed
toward Wellness
um with those particular
medicines I mean like I said we grew up
with with Homeopathy
um but I had always ear infections
and then sinus infections and throat and
and laryngitis and all these infectious
diseases why
because we ate a lot of dairy because my
parents thought that was really really
healthy
so you know and as soon as I cut out
Dairy I've never had an ear infection
again
I even can say that when my kids were
young and I was hired as a teacher in a
Waldorf School and I was
also having a corporate job and I was
doing this double job and the kids and
everything and they were always offering
pizza at the school so I thought ah come
on I'm so healthy I can handle it
Boom the biggest ear infection I've ever
had
so for me cheese cannot be overridden by
any Homeopathy it just can't it's too
powerful
a destructive or a destructive evening
um element in the human body
um so that's that's my answer to that
it's a wonderful those are wonderful
modalities in addition to a healthy
lifestyle
but they cannot fix an unhealthy
lifestyle if the unhealthy lifestyle
continues that's my my experience and
point of view so
and I know in your case Nancy you've
been a vegan for how long
only 50 years
I love that yes and do you eat mostly
organic
only organic there you go and mostly Raw
there you go that's why you're still
running
yeah but I'm so I'm very so athletic you
know basketball everything all like yeah
and
um I have I sometimes you know go flying
and falling and everything
um my chin up bar fell out of the out of
the holder and dropped me on my knees
because my my feet were up so you know I
I break bones occasionally and stuff
like that
um because I am so active and I found
that the homeopathic like arnica and you
know hyperigum and stuff like that it
heals it so much faster I mean you know
they say bones break and you need eight
weeks like for me it takes like five
days or something like that and I'm back
on my feet
so yeah I just wanted to offer that if
you are plant-based vegan organic
Raw
um holistic
Etc
um and I do an a no uh salt oil no SOS
salt oil
um add to that you know
um but for me it's it's been my teeth
and I want to kind of
like just keep them really healthy and
and that kind of thing
um so
yeah
kudos to you it's so good oh of course
my father actually showed us the arnica
plants we always had arnica oil and so
forth for for rubbing on not for eating
um and um my father showed us the arnica
plants in the Alps we went mountain
climbing with him and so I'm very
familiar with a lot of the the elements
and and yeah they absolutely help
and but so does ginger and garlic and
cayenne pepper you know when when I
twisted my foot really badly
instead of going to the hospital or
anything I just and it was like a big
blue purple thing my foot I just put
piles of Ginger with cayenne and I
didn't use garlic ginger and cayenne but
I eat a lot of garlic
um in a like a poultice not directly on
the skin but in a class folded up on my
foot repeatedly and it just like you
said it just takes days to heal with the
right
um
the right um
medicines that are from nature
and I mean we can talk more about
difficult situations that might be
um where we might think they're
difficult to heal
um
such as I was just looking up spider
bites because
um one of my clients had had a spider
bite before she was my client and ended
up with systemic inflammation which is
which is very dangerous it can be deadly
in a hospital they did all sorts of
things to
um get her out of this inflammation and
I was thinking ah you know a ginger
POTUS and going on to high green
cruciferous green smoothies with a
little bit of flex and kind of the the
protocol of Dr goldner
um
would have done the trick
would have fixed that
and I haven't another spiders story
um my colleague
fully raw Christina
um she goes by fully raw Christina
had a black spider bite in the jungle
somewhere and
and just decided okay I'm only going to
eat
watermelon and for two weeks she ate
nothing but natural watermelon with
seeds and she had
an indigenous person
put poltices of I think in that case it
was like a basil and garlic mix
onto that bite and it healed perfectly
fine and she had no traces of
um of the spider poisons which is
supposed to last for a long time in your
body no Trace left so
um
so yeah it's interesting that we can
even in those very difficult situations
that we can self-heal and so self-heal
for cheap is also that you don't need to
run to the emergency room if you know
some of these modalities and you trust
your ability to
self-heal and you trust your body's
ability which of course is the the last
part you know the joyful
gratitude gratitude Rich
um
hey David
I don't know you but I'm happy to see
another face because so many people just
stay anonymous
um
I am
yeah it just makes such a difference
that when we know some of those
modalities we literally do not need to
go to doctors I haven't been to doctors
in 20 years either
um
yeah sometimes there are situations no
even I mean I got into the car accident
now three years back
and um
I was T-boned
and everybody wanted me to go check up
and the insurance wouldn't pay unless
you go check up so finally I had them
you know I had a checkup and there was
nothing I literally crawled feet first
out of the totaled car and there was
nothing
in my body I mean I needed a few days of
rest to come down from the shock and but
I did not have
I didn't even have broken bones so
um of course that's not to say that
that's always the case
however we are more likely to
survive self-heal and rebalance again
back to what I said in the very
beginning that balance of the Symphony
of Life comes back together
when we have the right nutrients the
right breathing the right
um air and water and sunshine and the
right mindset and I'm tired of the word
mindset you know as if it fixes
everything and it makes you rich in two
days and so forth so I'm like I don't
really like the word mindset anymore
that much
but it still means that when you are
aware of your own healing power
you can
together with the biology you can fix
everything faster
and everything
more happily if that makes sense more
joyfully
um but many aches and pains also go away
just with the deep breathing method
and of course you know Wim Hof has
helped thousands of people millions of
people now around the globe to um
to get to that point where they are
confident that just with the deep
breathing method and the cold water
exposure
um
the body begins that biological cell
fixing
so
yeah any more questions
everybody is happy with everything I
said nobody has come on give me some
give me some counter here
give me some yeah but
I want to talk about I want to hug I
want to hear some I thought I thought
this would be an hour and I have to
leave yeah of course and it was supposed
to be an hour but we do go overboard
sometimes Andrea do you want to
contribute I just want to say what what
but could there possibly be these are
like just the fundamental principles of
life air fresh air healthy circulating
beautiful airs Sunshine
movement Joy luscious nourishment that
the Great Goddess mother provides for us
right there what we should be doing is
permaculturing the entire public sphere
of course yes all that natural food so
Bravo for you for putting together a
wonderful presentation
thank you thank you so much yeah I of
course I want you all to implement
Implement Implement Implement and many
of us need a helping hand I certainly do
again and again go to other people to I
just actually
um appointed a colleague of mine to call
me every day
to keep me on track with a particular
goal that I want to set before the I
have set before the end of the month so
if you need somebody to help you through
particular phases for example the
smoothie cleanse or the um what's coming
up oh a virtual Retreat is coming up
that's only 47 and you can sign up for
it
um
where can you sign up for it
oh I think I I created a link yeah so
you need to you need to let me know that
you want to sign up for it
um it's on the 27 28 29 and even though
my client clients are in there it's open
to the public and you can for three days
intensively get into some more of this
work that that leads to this great
health that so many of us in here are
actually experiencing in the second half
of life or the third part of life right
and that third part of life can be the
best ever you know why
because if your body is fully
functioning
and your mind is happy you have all this
experience of Decades of life
that you can put to work in this part of
life
and it's incredibly rewarding when you
figure out that you're not the old wood
you know delegated to the rocking chair
or to worse the nursery home and fed
with drugs and
oh
crap food
um
but you are actually a viable incredibly
valuable resource and
contribution to society so that's why
that's why it's important to self-heal
for cheap because we need all of the
mind's hearts and souls
that are ready to provide their
experience to the world and others in
these coming decades very very important
because there will be more chaos there
will be more more
um yeah especially Financial chaos over
the next so many years
it's to be expected
so creating new systems
will largely rely upon us old folks
because we have experienced the damage
that the old system
did
and we have created many of us new ways
of being and new ways of being healthy
is just part of new ways of being and
being creative
so let's end here
if there are no more questions uh
Joanna yes surely yes thank you so much
you're an inspiration everyone needs a
renewal constantly where as they age yes
surely will you share how old you are
right
almost
I've never told anybody debate 80s
late 80s that is beautiful and surely I
know Shirley has been a plant-based High
raw person for decades as well and is
yeah I was taking care of my husband for
like four straight Years Around the
Clock the lack of sleep
very stressful he was in attorney
addicted to stress
but I kept singing with him you know
yeah behind me he just passed away and
it's been very challenging so I ate
something because a lack of sleep
well no but now you're you're going to
perk yourself back up to give us another
few more years of your presence on
planet Earth that's right okay that's a
great last word we want to close out so
people don't feel I'm stretching this
out forever but I love you guys and I'm
going to email every one of you the the
offerings that I'm making here and that
200 offer for the next super happy body
class
as long as people are coming from this
Mastermind that's going to be the offer
it starts on February 7th so
we have a short time to get that done
ciao everybody
[Music]
so cool to have so many fabulous people
in here edwardinsky you are you should
be visible too I've known you for a long
time
you're struggling with finding the right
path to self-healing
get with the program ciao